#大家好 現在秋天啦 要給那個竹鼠啊 放點那個稻草
Hi everyone! It's now autumn. We need to put some straw for the bamboo rats.
#你看
Look!
#這個鎖都被我弟撬了
The lock was broken by my younger brother.
#上次
Last time,
#上之他找鎖匙找不到
he couldn't find the key,
#就直接撬了開門
and then he simply broke in.
#你看 這裡都
Look! Here was,
#撬得
deformed,
#被他撬歪啦
deformed by him.
#這裡 我剛剛釘回去啦
I've just nailed this part back to the door.
#太粗魯了
He's too brutal.
#你看
Look!
#這裡 這裡將近
Here, here're almost,
#三百多捆哦
more than three hundred bunches.
這裡一捆捆 三百多捆那個稻草
They're in bunches, more than three hundred bunches of straw.
#都準備好給竹鼠冬過冬的
They're here for the bamboo rats during the winter.
#這個今年的稻草 我們準 準備的比較豐富
We've pre, prepared plenty of straw this year.
#去年 去年就吃了點虧
Last year, we had a hard time last year.
#那個稻草
The straw,
#到春天的時候就沒有啦
was used up in spring.
#春天的時候不是很潮濕嗎
It was humid in spring, wasn't it?
#但是沒稻草
But we had no more straw.
#現在就
And now,
#今年就多稻啦
this year we have a lot.
#下面那個新場地我們都放了兩
There are like two, two to three hundred bunches,
#也放了兩三百捆
of this kind of straw,
#這個稻草下去
in the new site too.
#給它們放一點稻草
I'll put some straw for them.
#這個稻草現在還不是很冷哦
The straw... Now it is not really that cold.
#就是晚上有點冷
It might be a bit cool at night.
#所以我們放稻草的時候 只放給那個懷孕的
So when we are distributing the straw, we only give it to those who are pregnant,
#跟那個 帶崽的 其他的還不能放那麼快
and those, with newborn babies. We can't give it to other rats at this moment.
#不然冬天又不夠啦
Otherwise we won't have enough for the winter.
#這個公的就不管他們
The males, well, they'll take care of themselves.
#反正現在公的有多了
I have enough male rats anyway.
#這個下崽了哦
It has new babies.
#下了有
There're
#四個
four.
#這邊 這邊也下了
Here, this one too.
#這邊就沒有下
But not this one.
#這個也下了
And this one too.
#這個沒
This one no.
#誒誒 下了
Eh, eh? Yes!
#差一點 想咬我
So close. It wants to bite me.
#給個稻草給它 (註︰這個錯誤量詞就不譯了)
Give it some straw.
#有稻草的我就不給啦 (註︰英語好像好難說得簡單，乾脆兩句合一算了)
I only give it to those,
#沒稻草的我就給一點
who don't have any straw.
#這個 這個
This one is, this one is,
#這個懷孕的
this one is pregnant.
#吃完了
Finished
#這個給一點
Give a bit to this one,
#不能給那麼多
not too much.
#給一點點就好了
Just a little bit is enough.
#你看 這一群都是公的哦
Look! These are all males.
#後備公鼠
Spare male rats.
#不給它們稻草給它
I'm not giving them any straw.
#它們 抱在一起互相取暖就好啦
They can stay warm simply by clinging together.
#打呀
Just fight!
#等下我燒開水哦
I'll boil the water.
#不是打架 是搶東西
They're not really fighting, but scrambling.
#他們不敢打的 只搶
They don't dare to fight, they just scramble.
#它敢打的話 它敢打的話 燒開水
If they dare, if they ever dare. Boiling water.
#今天晚上 燉竹鼠
Dinner tonight, braised bamboo rat.
#啊 你看 這三個它們在搶
Ah! Look! These three rats are also scrambling for the food.
#自己吃自己的
Everyone has your own share.
#不要搶哦 不要打架哦
No scrambling! No fighting!
#怕甚麼 那麼怕
Why are you so scared?
#起來 我看一下 檢查一下
Get up! Let me have a look, have a check.
#這是公的
This is male.
#你看它的身材
Look at its body.
#特別苗條
It's really slim.
#我來了你還能吃
How can you be still eating when I am around?
#不跟我打下招呼啊
Don't you need to say hi to me?
#看有沒有還孕
Let me see if it's pregnant.
#摸一摸就知道它有多少個崽
I can find out the number of babies by feeling it.
#它不配合
It's uncooperative.
#到這裡來
Do it here.
#誒 莫得崽 (註︰客家話？)
Ey! No babies.
#不聽話 還想咬我
Naughty! It wants to bite me.
#這個養竹鼠啊 冬天的時候一定要準備好稻草 (註︰竹鼠養殖教學視頻完結時一般都是劉老師的課堂總結，會譯得較準確)
To raise bamboo rats, it's important to get the straw ready for the winter.
#如果不準備好稻草的話
If there's not enough straw,
#很多都會那個
many rats will, I mean,
#小崽啊 大鼠是沒有甚麼問題 (註︰口吃還是要譯)
the babies, I mean the adults will still be fine.
#小鼠崽很容易被凍 凍僵
But the babies will be easily frozen.
#凍僵了那個母的 它就不會要了
Then the mother will abandon them.
#會把它丟去外面去
They'll be thrown out of the cells.
#這樣就會做成那個 存活率特別低
This will significantly decrease the survival rate.
#所以我們都準備了將近五六百捆啊 那個稻草
That's why we've prepared more than half a thousand bunches of straw.
#給我放這裡 那邊也有 新場地那邊也有很多
Here, there, and also a lot in our new site.
#這個稻草又不值多少個錢
The straw doesn't cost a lot of money.
#幾百塊錢就能買五六百捆出來
Half a thousand bunches cost only several hundreds RMB.
#好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.